海洋 似乎了无边际
The oceans, seemingly limitless,
让我们充满敬畏和惊叹 有时也让我们心生畏惧
invoke in us a sense of awe and wonder and also, sometimes, fear.
它们占据了地表的70% 然而我们却依然对其
They cover 70% of the surface of our planet and yet they are still
知之甚少
the least explored.
隐藏在波涛之下 就在我脚下的水里
Hidden beneath the waves, right beneath my feet,
生活着我们想象不到的生物
there are creatures beyond our imagination.
在新技术的帮助下 我们能够进入崭新的世界
With revolutionary technology, we can enter new worlds...
以前人不可能完成的方式
..and shine a light on behaviours in ways that were impossible
探究海洋生物的行为
just a generation ago.
我们也意识到一个不安的现实
We've also recognised an uncomfortable fact...
我们的海洋正受到健康威胁
The health of our oceans is under threat.
它正以人类历史上前所未有的速度改变着
They are changing at a faster rate than ever before in human history.
趁现在来揭示海面下发生的一切
Never has there been a more crucial time to reveal what is going on
比任何时候都更为重要
beneath the surface of the seas.
在第一集中
In this first episode,
我们将抵达地球的各个海域
we will journey across the globe
从温暖的热带水域
from the warm waters of the Tropics
一路到最寒冷的极地水域
to the coldest around the poles...
让我们对海面下的生命有一个全新的认识
..to bring us a new understanding of life beneath the waves.
这里是蓝色星球Ⅱ
This is Blue Planet II.
许多生物潜藏在海面之下
The surface of the ocean conceals many creatures that live beneath.
但也有例外
But not all.
宽吻海豚
Bottlenose dolphins.
它们极其聪明
They are extremely intelligent.
伴随智慧而来的是顽皮
And with this intelligence comes playfulness.
它们喜欢冲浪 而且据我们所知
They surf and, as far as we can tell,
它们这样做完全是为了好玩
they do so for the sheer joy of it.
但要想真正了解他们的性情
But to properly appreciate their true character,
你必须跟着他们 进入它们的世界
you have to travel with them into their world.
一群宽吻海豚
A pod of bottlenose dolphins
正拜访一处位于红海的珊瑚礁
is visiting a coral reef in the Red Sea.
对小海豚来说 学习的时候到了
For the youngsters, there are things to be learned here.
成年海豚领着一只小海豚来到一个灌木形状的珊瑚旁
The adults lead a calf to a particular bush-like coral
这是柳珊瑚
called a gorgonian.
在这里 成年海豚做出了一个奇怪的举动
And here the adults behave rather strangely.
他们故意从珊瑚上擦过
They deliberately rub themselves through the fronds.
小家伙似乎不愿意这样做
Their calf seems reluctant to do so.
但看见长辈们都这样做
By watching his elders,
他也许意识到了自己也必须这样做
he may be realising that this is something he ought to do.
实际上 柳珊瑚表面
Gorgonian fronds, in fact,
覆盖着一层粘液
are covered with a mucus that can have anti-inflammatory
具有消炎抗菌的功效
and antimicrobial properties.
所以成年海豚这样做也许是为了
So maybe the adult dolphins are doing this
防止皮肤感染
to protect themselves from infection.
海豚关于珊瑚礁的丰富知识
The dolphins' intimate knowledge of the reef
也启发我们在这里寻找新药物
is spurring us to search for new medicines here, too.
热带珊瑚礁只占海床总面积的0.1%
Tropical coral reefs occupy only a tenth of 1% of the ocean floor.
但这片有着全年稳定条件的温暖浅水区
But their shallow warm waters and stable year-round conditions
却供养着海洋里最丰富多样的
support some of the most crowded and varied communities
生物群落
to be found anywhere in the oceans.
每一个物种都有待研究
And there are new discoveries to be made on every one of them.
在澳大利亚的大堡礁 生活着一种鱼
One creature on Australia's Great Barrier Reef is challenging our
它颠覆了我们对鱼智慧的认识
understanding of fish intelligence.
一只猪齿鱼
A tuskfish.
你很快就会明白它名字的由来
And you can see why it gets its name.
他做的事很少有人相信鱼能做到
He does something few would have believed a fish could do.
每天早晨他游到珊瑚礁边缘
Every morning he travels to the edge of the reef.
他在珊瑚残骸和沙子中
He is searching for something special to eat amongst the coral
寻找一种特殊的食物
rubble and sand.
找到了一个
Here is one.
一只小蛤蜊
A small clam.
但怎样才能把它打开 吃到里面的肉呢
But how to crack it open and get to the meat?
他把它一路带回自己的私人厨房
He takes it all the way back to his special kitchen.
一个碗状珊瑚
A bowl-shaped coral
里面有处可以用于故技重施的凸起
that has a particular bump on the inside that he always uses.
没有手的话这将是件很困难的事
It's not easy if you have no hands.
喔 又没中
Whoops, there he goes again.
但他有极大的决心
But he's got great determination...
和惊人的准确性
..and surprising accuracy.
终于
At last!
所以这是一只会使用工具的鱼
So here is a fish that uses tools.
有些鱼比你想象的聪明得多
Some fish are much cleverer than you might suppose.
热带珊瑚礁里密集的生物群落
The density of the animals on tropical reefs
使得竞争不可避免而异常激烈
makes competition inevitable and extreme.
不只是对于那些居住在珊瑚礁里的生物
Not only for those that live within the reefs...
对在上面飞着的鸟儿也是一样
..but for the birds that fly above them.
在旱季
During the dry season,
超过五十万只乌燕鸥飞到这个偏远的
over half a million terns crowd onto this remote atoll
印度洋环礁岛上
in the Indian Ocean.
它们的雏鸟还披着未长成的黑色绒羽
Their chicks are still in their dark juvenile plumage.
它们年龄大小各不相同
They vary in age.
当大些的飞向天空时
Whilst the more advanced chicks take to the air..
小点的还飞不起来
..others aren't quite ready yet.
岛屿中心浅浅的环礁湖成为了
Those just starting to learn to fly use the shallow lagoon that occupies
这些幼鸟的飞行训练场
the centre of the atoll as their training ground.
对部分幼鸟而言 长时间停留在空中还很困难
It's difficult for some of them to stay aloft for long.
珍鲹
Giant trevally.
它们通常单独捕食
Usually they are solitary hunters.
但在天降美食的诱惑下 会有50只左右的珍鲹
But about 50 of them have come here from neighbouring reefs,
从附近的珊瑚礁赶来赴宴
attracted by this abundance of potential prey.
幼鸟尽量不在水面做任何停留
The fledglings stay out of the water if they can.
连喝水的时候也不落下来
They even drink on the wing.
如果珍鲹现在要抓到它们
If the trevally are to catch one now,
就必须加大筹码
they have to up their game.
所以一只鱼 能够不可思议地
So there was a fish here that, amazingly,
计算出空气的流速
has a brain capable of calculating the airspeed,
鸟的飞行高度和轨迹
altitude and trajectory of a bird.
幼鸟们飞向天空
The time comes when every fledgling has to take to the air
独立觅食的时候到了
and collect food for itself.
它们的父母把它们领到训练场
Their parents lead them to the training grounds.
要想活下去
If they are to survive,
它们必须尽快学会飞翔
they must learn quickly.
在环礁湖上训练一个月后
After a month of practising over the lagoon,
幼鸟们便开始离开 踏上翻洋过海的征程
the youngsters start to leave and take their chances over the open sea.
海洋中的水占地球总水量的97%
The oceans hold 97% of all the water in the world.
当太阳照到水面 水分蒸发
As the sun warms the surface, water evaporates.
蒸气升腾到空中
It vaporises into the sky until it cools and condenses
直到遇冷凝结成云
into towering clouds.
它们产生巨大的风暴
And they generate huge storms.
地球自转使这些气旋向南北分散
The spin of the Earth deflects these storms north and south
进入高纬地区
into cooler latitudes.
它们经过海面时
As they travel across the sea,
风暴掀起万丈狂澜
storm-driven winds create huge swells.
当波澜到达浅水区
When the swells reach shallower water,
就会变成滔天巨浪
they rise into gigantic waves.
一次大风暴释放的能量
In it lifetime, a large storm can release energy
相当于一万颗核弹的威力
that is the equivalent of 10,000 nuclear bombs.
这些是季节性海域
These are the seasonal seas.
当春暖人间时 它们就会爆发出蓬勃的生命力
And when they warm in spring, they can suddenly explode with life.
大量的蝠鲼聚集在墨西哥的科斯特湾
Mobula rays have gathered in Mexico's Sea of Cortez in vast numbers.
它们为什么跃出水面
Why do they leap?
是要告诉同类自己在这吗
Is it to tell others that they are here?
没有人知道
No-one knows.
他们大多在晚上觅食
They feed mostly at night,
因为那时 大量的浮游生物会从海底涌上来
for that is when vast swarms of plankton rise from the depths.
海水的扰动
The disturbance in the water stimulates many
使得许多浮游生物发出微光
of the planktonic creatures to luminesce.
现在我们可以借助新的摄影技术 拍到这些微光
Only now do we have the technology to record their faint glow.
觅食的蝠鲼在这些微光间穿梭
The feasting rays swim through them,
演绎一支生与死的芭蕾
creating an extraordinary ballet of life and death.
这些海域的富饶得益于丰富的微生植物
The richness of these waters is based on microscopic plants -
浮游植物 无比繁盛的它们造福了整个生物圈
phytoplankton - which bloom on such a massive scale they benefit us all.
它们 连同海草和海藻
They, together with seaweeds and sea grasses,
制造的氧气足以胜过于陆地上所有森林和草场的总和
produce as much oxygen as all the forests and grassy plains on land.
每年春天 新西兰沿岸季节性的富足
Every spring, off New Zealand, the seasonal bounty
引来了难得的访客
draws in rare visitors.
伪虎鲸
False killer whales.
它们和虎鲸有亲缘关系
They are relatives of the orca,
身长六米 体重超过一吨
six metres long and weighing over a tonne.
它们似乎正在搜寻海豚
They appear to be searching for dolphins.
沿岸的水域有很多
And there are many in these coastal waters.
这里 一群宽吻海豚在一起游动
Here, bottlenose dolphins stick together,
不断地用超声波相互交流
constantly chattering with whistles and clicks.
这种声音在水下能传到几英里外的地方
Such a din carries for miles underwater.
伪虎鲸侦查到了它们
The false killers have detected them.
十个一群 这些杀手朝他们围拢过来
Travelling at ten knots, the killers quickly close in on them.
但突然 神奇的事情发生了
But then, something truly extraordinary happens.
海豚转过身来 就像问候这些伪虎鲸一样
The dolphins turn, as if to greet their pursuers.
它们似乎改变了方向
They seem to change their course.
他们是否有可能是在尝试交流呢
Could it be that they are attempting to communicate?
研究它们这一行为的科学家现在认为
Scientists studying this annual encounter now think that
它们个体之间可能相互认识
individuals may recognise one another.
出乎意料地
Almost unbelievably,
两个不同的物种居然是老相识
it seems that these different species appear to be old friends.
他们一起组成一支大军 数量达一千之多
Together they are gathering as one unified army, up to 1,000-strong.
这个巨大的捕猎队伍现在要去收获
This formidable hunting party now harvests the riches
伴随新西兰夏季而来的自然馈赠
that come with New Zealand's summer.
在中纬度地区
All across the higher latitudes,
季节性海域在夏日的阳光下焕发出蓬勃生机
seasonal seas flourish under the summer sun.
在阿拉斯加
Here in Alaska,
海獭在海底森林的树冠上晒太阳
sea otters lounge in the canopy of great submarine forests.
巨藻 世界上最大的藻类 是各种海洋生物的家
Giant kelp, the biggest seaweed of all, is home to all kinds of life.
在这片森林的地面上 浑身带刺的海胆啃食着巨藻
On the forest floor, spiny sea urchins munch through the kelp.
另一处 是不断进食的海参
Elsewhere, there are continuously hungry sea cucumbers.
在下面缠绕的水草中间 是伪装自己的叶海马
And in the tangled undergrowth, wonderfully camouflaged sea dragons.
在日本北部的海底森林
In the underwater forests of northern Japan,
一艘沉船上的居民们
the residents of the sunken wreck
正等待着水温上升到
are waiting for the summer temperatures
十六摄氏度
to reach 16 Celsius.
对于一些居民来说 那意味着交配的时间到了
That, for some, is the time for mating.
金黄突额隆头鱼 当地叫它Kobudai
A kind of giant wrasse called a Kobudai.
这是一只雄性
This is a male.
以雌鱼的眼光来看 他非常英俊
And in female terms, he is particularly handsome.
他身长一米 体重十五公斤
He's a metre long and weighs 15 kilos.
比身边的雌鱼大很多
Much larger than the diminutive female.
他准备好交配了
And he is ready to breed.
他试图和她交配
He attempts to mate with her -
还有住在他领地里的另外十多只雌鱼
and with any of the other dozen or so females that live in his territory
只要他逮着机会
whenever he gets the chance.
但年约十岁的雌性
But females from around ten years old
却不为所动
take little notice of his advances.
这是因为当雌鱼的体型达到一定程度
This is because when any large female reaches a critical body size,
就会经历身体上的巨大转变
she could begin a dramatic transformation.
几个月内
Over just a few months,
她体内的某些酶停止工作
particular enzymes inside her body cease to work.
雄性荷尔蒙开始分散到全身的各个部位
And male hormones started to circulate.
一段时间后
As time passes,
她的头部隆起 下巴变长
her head expands and her chin gets longer.
她变成了他
A she has changed into a he.
性情也随之大变
And with this comes a change in temperament.
以前统领这里的雄鱼
The old male who ruled all the females here.
受到了挑战
..is challenged to a face-off.
头越大 越能吓住对手
The more bulbous the head, the more it intimidates an opponent.
这片领地有了新主人
The territory has a new ruler.
只有体型最大的雌鱼才会经历这种转变
Only the largest females transform themselves in this way.
这种转变使得它们获得更多的交配机会
But the change enables them to have more mates,
所以就会有更多的后代携带它们的优良基因
so they will have many more offspring carrying their genes.
但新主人也不能掉以轻心
But a new male can't afford to be complacent.
因为在每一只雌性Kobudai的身体里
Inside the body of every Kobudai female,
都蛰伏着一个新的雄性
there is a new male in waiting.
越往两极 海水的温度越低
The closer we travel towards poles, the colder the seas become.
海面开始出现冰山
Icebergs appear,
从冰川上崩落到海里的
huge slabs that have broken away
巨大冰块
from glaciers that are sliding into the sea.
然后海面开始结冰
And then the surface starts to freeze.
当极光在空中舞蹈
While the lights of the aurora play above,
即使在冬季最冷的时候
even in the depths of midwinter,
北极圈内的某些地方
there are a few places well north of the Arctic Circle
海面依然没有封冻
that are still open.
一股巨大的洋流使得挪威北部的峡湾没有结冰
The fjords of northern Norway remain ice-free because a giant current,
墨西哥湾暖流
the Gulf Stream,
从南部的加勒比海带来热量
flows up here from the south, bringing warmth all the way from the Caribbean.
每年冬天 数以亿计的鲱鱼来这里越冬
And every winter, billions of herring come here for shelter.
紧随其后的是
And following them...
虎鲸
..orca.
有1000只之多
There are up to 1,000 of them.
这也许是世界上规模最大的虎鲸集体活动
It's possibly the greatest gathering of orca on the planet.
虽然鲱鱼很多
The herring may be plentiful,
但要想在广阔的峡湾地带抓住它们可不容易
but in these widening fjords they're not always easy to track down.
但这些虎鲸可是专业的捕鱼能手
These particular orca, however, are fish-hunting specialists.
它们团结组队
They work as a team,
相互之间通过声音交流协作
coordinating their approach by calling loudly to one another.
把鲱鱼群赶得越来越密
They herd the herring into tighter and tighter shoals.
然后游到它们下方 把它们赶向水面
They swim below them, trapping them against the surface of the sea.
现在虎鲸使出了它们的杀手锏
And now the orca deploy their special weapon.
他们振尾一甩 冲击波将鲱鱼击昏
They beat their tails with such force that the shockwaves stun the herring.
然后它们不费吹灰之力地将毫无知觉的鲱鱼吃进肚里
And then the senseless victims are easily collected.
水下巨大的动静也引来了其他的捕食者
But all this underwater noise attracts others.
座头鲸
Humpback whales.
他们也加入进来
They move in on the action.
它们从下方靠拢鱼群 然后猛冲上来
They approach the shoal from beneath and then lunge upwards...
一口能吞下100公斤的鲱鱼
...gathering up to 100 kilos of herring in a single mouthful.
座头鲸相对算是此地的新住户
The humpbacks are comparative newcomers.
它们是近十年才开始来这里的
They only started coming here within the last decade.
但这些鲱鱼数量如此庞大
But these policies are so rich
似乎没有出现争抢食物的局面
that there appears to be enough food for everyone.
但是 要是没有这支洋流
Nonetheless, few, if any,of these riches would be here
这里就不会有这种丰饶和富足
were it not for the Gulf Stream.
事实上 洋流对地球的健康至关重要
Ocean currents, in fact, are crucial to the wellbeing of our planet.
它们把太阳的热量
They distribute the sun's heat towards the poles
从赤道一路带到两极
all the way from the Equator,
使得几乎地球上的各个角落都适合生物的生存
maintaining a climate favourable for life almost everywhere.
调节气候 制造氧气
From creating the weather to producing oxygen,
海洋保持着我们这颗星球的健康
the seas keep our world healthy.
但一些令人担忧的迹象表明
But there are now worrying signs that
千年来一直保持着相对稳定的海洋环境
conditions in the oceans that have remained relatively stable for millennia
正在发生剧烈的改变
are changing rapidly.
没有什么地方比北极体现得更明显
Nowhere is this more evident than in the Arctic.
过去的30年里
Here in the past 30 years,
北极夏季的冰川总量减少了40%
the extent of the ice in summer has been reduced by 40%.
这种急剧变暖 极可能是人类活动的结果
This sudden warming, most likely a consequence of human activity,
这正对野生动物造成深远影响
is having a profound impact on its wildlife.
海象就是最大的受害者之一
Walruses are among those that are seriously affected.
每个成年母亲都需要给她80公斤的宝宝
Every adult female needs to find a safe place
找一个休憩的场所
where her 80-kilo pup can rest.
他们原地盘上的海冰大多都在消融
The sea ice is retreating from much of the walruses' traditional range
所以现在他们只能躺在干燥的地面上
so they now have to haul out on dry land.
但一百多只好斗的母亲 一些体重接近一吨
But a herd of hundreds of quarrelsome mothers -
挤在一起 可不是理想的的育儿场所
some weighing almost a tonne - is not an ideal nursery.
海象在陆地上待在一起是很明智的
Walruses on land stick together for good reason.
北极熊
Polar bears.
一只成年雄海象体型巨大
A full-grown male walrus is gigantic -
北极熊也不敢轻举妄动
too big for even a polar bear to tackle.
她要找的是海象宝宝
So the bear is looking for a walrus baby.
海象们嗅到北极熊的气味
The scent of the bear spreads alarm to the colony.
纷纷退回海里
The walruses retreat into the sea.
北极熊知道在水下抓不到它们
The bear knows it won't be able to catch them there.
但她也有孩子要喂养
But she, too, has young ones to feed.
一个母亲又能如何呢
What is a mother to do?
一个海象母亲需要找个地方 让孩子休息
A mother walrus still needs to find a place where her young can rest.
一块正在融化的冰山就很好
A melting iceberg might do.
但已经有人捷足先登了
But she is not the first to find this one.
合适的位置已经被占了
Suitable places are already taken.
其他的母亲不愿意分享
Other mothers don't want to share.
她们也需要地方来保护她们的孩子
They, too, need a patch of ice where they can protect their young.
绝望的母亲只能强取豪夺
A desperate mother has no choice but to barge her way in.
所以这下好了 都没得地方休息了
So this time, everyone loses.
要在这些正在消融的冰岸上找个合适的休憩之所
Finding the right place on these melting shores
越来越困难
gets harder and harder.
共同解决这些问题
Solving these problems together
能够帮助母子双方 在余生里
helps create a bond so strong that the mother will stay in contact with her young
建起一种强大的纽带
for the rest of her life.
但谁又知道它们的未来会怎样呢
But who knows now what their future will be?
随着我们对海洋生物
As we understand more about the complexity
的了解加深
of the lives of sea creatures,
我们开始珍惜它们脆弱的家园
so we begin to appreciate the fragility of their home,
我们的蓝色星球
our blue planet.
蓝色星球II拍摄历时四年
Blue Planet II has been four years in the making.
拍摄足迹遍布四大洋
The teams have explored every ocean,
记录下很多不为人知的非凡故事 其中很多都是科学上的新发现
discovering extraordinary untold stories, many new to science.
让我们对海面下的生命有新的认识和了解
Bringing a new understanding of life beneath the waves.
最新的潜水科技 能够不产生气泡和噪音
The latest diving technology, producing no bubbles or noise,
使我们的摄影队伍能够长时间近距离地进行拍摄
has allowed our teams longer and closer encounters.
为了探索深海
To explore our final frontier, the deep,
我们在潜水器里呆了1000个小时
we've spent 1,000 hours in submersibles
那是超过半英里深的水下
over half a mile below the surface.
创新的摄影技术帮助我们
Innovative new camera technology makes it possible
拍到以前从未拍到过的景象
to film moments never seen before.
极度低光摄像机能捕捉到肉眼看不见的神奇景象
Lowlight cameras capture magical events almost invisible to the naked eye.
探测摄像头给了我们
Probe cameras give a completely fresh perspective
观察微小生物的全新视角
into the lives of tiny creatures...
来了 它来了
Here it comes, here it comes.
吸盘摄像机能够让我们以鲸的视野看海洋
..while suction cameras take us on a giant's-eye view of the ocean.
但在海上工作世事难料 也很危险
But the sea is an unpredictable and dangerous place to work.
特别是所谓的 南非狂野海岸
Nowhere more so than the so-called wild coast of South Africa...
冲浪海豚的家
..home to surfing dolphins.
摄制组的任务是和冲浪海豚一道前行
The team's mission here is to ride alongside the dolphins
以前所未有的细致记录下它们的冲浪行为
and record their surfing behaviour in closer detail than ever before.
这些海域不可捉摸 所以摄制组请来了当地的冲浪专家做向导
These are treacherous seas so the film crew enlists local professional surfers to guide them.
但今年 浪比任何人预想的都大
But this year, the waves are bigger than anyone had anticipated.
这让冲浪摄影师克里斯·瑞恩感到很紧张
A daunting prospect for surf cameraman Chris Ryan.
对 我感到很紧张
Yeah, I'm feeling pretty nervous...
海面上有巨大的涌浪
It's a big swell out there.
真的是很大的涌浪
Really big swell.
浪足有20英尺高
There's 20ft waves out there and...
对 这也许是我去过的最危险的海域
..yeah, this will probably be the biggest sea I've ever been out in.
我想 没有付出 就没有回报
No risk, no reward, I guess.
克里斯有一个高速摄像机能够拍到海浪中的
Chris has a high-speed camera to shoot super-slow-motion action
超慢镜头
in the waves.
挑战是要尽量接近
The challenge is to get as close
冲浪的海豚
to the wave-riding dolphins as possible.
好消息是我们在地平线上发现了海豚
The good news is that the dolphins have been spotted on the horizon.
他们说这是今年最大的浪
They said this was going to be the biggest swell of the year
我从没见过这种场面
hey, I've never seen anything like this.
这浪比我想像的可大多了
This is much bigger than I had possibly imagined.
在这种时候 只有摩托艇能接近海豚
In these waves, the only way to get out to the dolphins is with a jet ski.
光是翻过那些巨浪
It's going to be enough of a challenge for them
就已经够困难的了
just to kind of weave their way out.
最终驾驶员精湛的技术
At last the driver's detailed knowledge
带他们安全越过了巨浪
gets them safely through the massive breakers.
但宽吻海豚不见了
But the dolphins are nowhere to be seen...
摄制组只得返回岸上
..leaving the crew to face the hair-raising task
但回来的路将会更惊险
of getting back to shore.
快 快 快
Go, go, go, go!
哦
Oh!
看见了吗 太疯狂了
How was that? That was pretty wild, yeah.
浪打到摩托艇的尾部 我不停地说 快点 快点 我们得赶快离开这
the wave actully hit the back of the sled and i was like go, go, get out of here, guys get out of here
赶快离开 它一下子撞上来差点反弹出去
"get out of here." It hit a big bump but almost bounced off
我一直紧紧抓住摄像机 一路冲回来 但是
I was trying to hold the camera and just rode out of there, but, yeah,
这真是太疯狂了
it was hectic.
又得回家剪片子了
Just another day at the office.
第二天天气陡然好转
The next day brings a sudden change in conditions.
有很多海豚
Plenty of dolphins
海面却很平静
but a calmer sea.
一点风浪都没有
A complete lack of any wave at all!
它们会出现的 会出现的
They'll come, they'll come, they'll come!
在海上
As so often in the ocean,
通常只要在正确的位置 你只需耐心等候
if you know you're in the right place, you just need the patience
时机的到来
to wait for the perfect moment.
一周后 又一次风暴在狂野海岸酝酿着
A week later and the storm is once again brewing off the wild coast,
海浪渐渐涌起
and surf is building.
我感到很激动
I feel, like, a nervous excitement.
拍摄的条件堪称完美
The conditions are absolutely perfect, this is
完全是我们想要的效果
completely what we've been waiting for.
海豚也好像知道（我们要拍它们）似的
And the dolphins seem to know it.
但克里斯没法平稳地拍摄
But Chris is struggling to get a steady shot.
那里怎么样
How about that?
嗨 先生们 太难了
Hello, gentlemen. Tricky.
在摩托艇上要找到合适的角度太难了
A little tricky on the jet ski just trying to get the right angle.
所以这次我跟左迪亚克一起去
So I'm going to have a go with the Zodiac
希望这次能成功
and hopefully have better luck on that one.
橡皮艇给了克里斯一个更大
The inflatable boat gives Chris a larger,
更平稳的摄影平台
more stable filming platform.
终于 时机正好
At last, he is in exactly the right place at exactly the right time.
结果堪称完美
And the results are spectacular.
任务圆满成功
Mission accomplished.
这些珍贵的影像
And this intimate footage is now available
为科学研究提供了资料
as part of wider scientific studies.
帮助证明海豚冲浪 是为了增进友谊
Supporting evidence that dolphins surf to strengthen friendships,
培养社交技能 以及获得快乐
develop social skills and for the sheer exhilaration of it.
下一期 深海
Next time, the deep.
一个比你想象中更丰富多彩的世界
A world richer than we ever thought possible,
地球最极端环境中
where creatures thrive
也有蓬勃的生机
in the most extreme conditions on Earth.
想获取这张免费海报 获取更多关于海洋的知识 请拨打
To find out more about our oceans with this free poster, call...
或者登陆
Or go to...
点击链接进入公开课
..and follow the links to the Open University.
Compressed by
DREAM TEAVELER
压制：失梦旅行
Effected by
WILDER
特效：歪二德
Translated by
THREE-WATER
翻译：三水
Proofreaded by
3 WATER & WILDER
校对：三水 歪二德
Supervised by
CHELLE
监制：杳杳
解说：大卫·爱登堡
它们环绕在你四周
此番景象在陆地上可看不到
我们什么也没看见
我们在绝对黑暗中拍摄
我们全然处于失明状态
制片人:乔纳森·史密斯
同   一   片   海
蓝 色 星 球 Ⅱ 幕 后
蓝色星球Ⅱ
(海洋藻类是地球氧气的主要来源)
(世界大洋中最强大的暖流)